Guide to the Karl E. Beckson papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Karl E. Beckson Papers,
1956-1993
[Bulk Dates: 1965-1992].
Beckson, Karl E., 1926-
2.5 linear ft. (6 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1515
6909765
This collection consists of research and publication materials, correspondence, and manuscripts of several of Karl Beckson's books. It includes a large amount of research materials for Beckson's biography of Arthur Symons.
Biographical Note
Karl Beckson was a professor of English literature and author of many articles and books on British literature and culture in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries.
He was born Emmanuel Beckson on February 4, 1926, and raised on the Upper East Side of Manhattan. After serving in the United States Navy during the Second World War, he earned a B.A. (1949) in English from the University of Arizona and an M.A. (1952) and Ph.D. (1959) from Columbia University, where he studied with Lionel Trilling and Mark Van Doren. He worked briefly at Columbia, Bronx Community College, and Fairleigh-Dickinson University before teaching at Brooklyn College, City University of New York, for the rest of his career. As a scholar, he took special interest in the late-nineteenth-century Symbolist movement and its influence on late-nineteenth- and early-twentieth-century writers such as James Joyce, D. H. Lawrence, and George Bernard Shaw. He wrote several books on Arthur Symons, Oscar Wilde, and Henry Harland, including biographies of Symons and Harland. He also co-wrote a dictionary of literary terms and edited several volumes of letters and memoirs. Beckson retired in 2004 and died on April 29, 2008.
Scope and Content
The collection contains research and publication materials, correspondence, and published writings. The research and publication materials consist of photocopies of letters and prints of photographs of Arthur Symons, Henry Harland, and other writers; correspondence with publishers, libraries, scholars, and friends of Symons; and publishing agreements. The published writings include manuscripts and galleys of several books written by Beckson between 1989 and 1993.
Arrangement
The contents of the collection are arranged alphabetically, following the titles that Beckson wrote on his folders.
Subjects
Harland, Henry, 1961-1905.; Symons, Arthur, 1865-1945.; English literature--19th century.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions. This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Karl E. Beckson Gift 1992
Karl E. Beckson
- Alphabetical Files
  - Research and Publication Materials
    - Academy Press, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Collier's Encyclopedia, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - [Columbia Rare Book and Manuscript Library], 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1966-1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Eighteen Nineties Society, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Farrar, Straus Agreement, 1962-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Fletcher, 1984-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Harland Material, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Harland Photos, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Hinzmann, 1987-1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - John Murray, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Kingsley, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Krishnamurti, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - [Lambourne, Lionel], 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Langenfeld, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lydia Lopokova Keynes, 1969-1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Macmillan, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Marbury Material, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Mason, 1956-1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Merlin Holland, 1981-1992 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Michael Holroyd, 1968-1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Mrs. Percy Grainger 1971-1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - [Osborne, Humfrey Photo], 1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Oxford, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Pennsylvania State University Press, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Permissions for Aesthetes and Decadents of the 1890s 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Permissions for Wilde volume, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Rhymers' Club, 1963-1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Sir John Rothenstein, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Tragara Press, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Woodring, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Wratislaw, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Symons: 1880-1903, 1980s, (23 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1 to 23)
    - Symons: 1904-1934, 1980s, (22 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1 to 22)
    - Symons--Undated (before 1908), 1980s (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Symons--Undated (after 1908), 1980s (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Symons at the Bodleian, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Symons at Buffalo, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Symons at Kansas, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Symons at Texas, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Symons at Yale, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Wills of Arthur and Rhoda, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - [Symons Permissions], 1980s (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Symons Permission for Biography, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Symons Permissions for Memoirs, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Symons Photographs, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Symons Correspondence, 1965-1986, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Published Writings
    - Arthur Symons: Selected Letters Manuscript, circa 1989, (3 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Arthur Symons: A Bibliography Portion of Manuscript, 1990, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Arthur Symons: A Bibliography Galleys, 1990, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Literary Terms: A Dictionary, Third Edition Manuscript, 1989, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 5 to 6)
    - London in the 1890s A Cultural History Manuscript, 1993, (3 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1 to 3)